Sand martins don’t do well alone. We are sociable creatures, it’s in our blood.
This was probably the first time in my entire life I had been truly alone, and it terrified me.
I looked at the grey sky, and that when I spotted another martin flying in the distance.
I called to him, but he didn’t hear me. So I took off and tried to catch up with him in the air.
“Excuse me”, I gasped.
He turned toward me.
“Hi”, he said. “You’re new here, aren’t you?”
“How do you know?” I asked. He didn’t reply. He smiled. It was the first smile I’d got since I arrived.
“Where are you going?” I asked.
“Hounslow”, he said. “In the suburbs. Did you really expect to find a decent place to stay in central London?” He laughed.
“Come on. I’ll show you.”
We flew for half an hour, following the river.
He asked me lots of questions, about my journey, about my family, about home.
You can always trust another sand martin to make you feel comfortable and have good chat.
Then suddenly, he pointed at something below on the riverbed and we landed.
Ahead of me was the most terrifying nest I had ever seen.
A gigantic construction of a dozen towers carved on the sandy faces of the bank, flanked by countless tiny windows.
And coming in and out of those holes: sand martins. There were hundreds of them, flying around and chittering in a terrible cacophony.
After the loneliness of the last few weeks, I was in shock.
“What is this?” I asked my companion.
“Our community”, he said. “Do you like it?”
I didn’t know what to answer. I had never seen so many birds living so close together.
“Is it safe?” Was my first thought. “What if there is a fire or something?”
He shrugged. “Look, this is a migrants’ nest. Of course it’s different from what you had back home. Less spacious. Colder. But it’s a good nest. You’ll get used to it. You just need to dive in.”
And he did. He flew inside one of the openings and disappeared.
I stood there, unsure about what to do. This was so different from anything I had imagined. How could this ever be home?
Then all of a sudden, I heard the voice of Nunyati in my head.
“Home is an elusive concept, Mawusi. You never know where you’ll find it.”
I looked at the giant nest. I could hear the sound of dozens of sand martins coming from within, chatting, laughing.
It was cold outside, it looked so much warmer inside.
So I closed my eyes. I took a deep breath. And I dove in.